Finding Aid for the Curtis Howe Walker Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Curtis Howe Walker Papers
1853-1960
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0483
1.26 linear feet
Biographical Sketch
Curtis Howe Walker, Ph.D. was on the faculty of Vanderbilt University as a Professor of European History, 1927-1947; Director of Social Science Orientation Course, 1929-1933, and Professor Emeritus of European History, 1948-1956.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains his 1905 thesis from Yale University, outgoing/incoming correspondence, a manuscript, some class notes, 70 photographs, a postcard collection [related to European travel depicting medieval architecture and religious themes], and 47 lantern slides.
In addition, the collection contains the correspondence between members of his mother’s family, the Johnston’s, during the Civil War; a scrapbook, and Turkish pictures presented to his mother when she came to America in 1853.
- Correspondence - Outgoing
  - Robert L. Schuyler, August 12, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Maxwell Perkins, November 11, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - W. D. Howe, May 7, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - W. K. Jordan, December 8, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John T. McNeil, June 4, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - H. S. Latham, July 15, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Paul R. Reynolds, Jr., August 29, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cecil Sims, September 5, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Paul R. Reynolds, Jr., September 7, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Rosemary B. York, September 9, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence - Incoming
  - Keller, April 19, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 5a)
  - Keller, April 28, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 5a)
  - F. J. Wickware, May 9, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jessica B. Mannon, July 16, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - F. J. Wickware, November 5, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jessica B. Mannon, January 11, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - L. Nalphey, February 19, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Eleanor Fleming, December 2, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - George Marion O’Donnell, July 27, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A. D. Hewes, October 7, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Wilbur Russell, December 7, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - T. Laehelier, October 19, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jo, January 8, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alice, January 21, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - James M. Osborn, March 8, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - C. Garnier, May 11, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Donald P. Bean, June 22, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Maxwell Perkins, February 15, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Maxwell Perkins, March 13, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Agnes Hewes, November 19, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Agnes Hewes, May 28, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Agnes Hewes, August 4, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Danny, October 9, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - unknown, November 3, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Maxwell Perkins, November 16, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - N. D. Howe, January 21, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Donald, October 13, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - W. K. Jordan, December 1, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - W. K. Jordan, December 15, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - H. S. Latham, January 11, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Catherine King, January 20, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Agnes Hewes, May 14, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - John T. McNeill, May 20, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - H. S. Latham, August 16, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - unknown, August 30, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Mary R. Braman, September 27, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pauline Woodard, June 16, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Alice Stockell, August 29, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Paul R. Reynolds, Jr., August 31, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cecil Sims, August 31, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rosemary B. York, August 31, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rosemary B. York, September 9, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Nicholas Wreden, January 31, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Nicholas Wreden, March 15, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - C. Arnold Guyot, April 29, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Wallace Notestein, January 21, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Henry A. Beers – relating to. Froude, December 13, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - William E. Dodd – relating to Froude, February 9, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - George Macaulay Trevelyan – relating to Froude, November 15, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence – Incoming - Postcards
  - Tom Webb, November 2, 1930 (Box 1)
  - R.Q.C., April 13, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Francis Robinson, December 6, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Ed, January 12, 1933 (Box 1)
  - n.s., April 7, 1937 (Box 1)
  - C, June 30, 1937 (Box 1)
  - M.R.B. (4 postcards w/two photographs), June, 1937 (Box 1)
  - H. Luc, May 26, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Mary Elizabeth Wilson, July 25, 1938 (Box 1)
  - C. U. Clark, November 24, 1939 (Box 1)
  - S, n.d (Box 1)
- Journal Article
  - “The ‘True’ Mr. Froude” reprinted from The Texas Review, July, 1923
- Literary Critiques and Reviews
  - “Eleanor of Aquitaine” - by Melrich V. Rosenberg, 1937
- Manuscript
  - “The Literary Battle of Hastings” - by Curtis Howe Walker, n.d.
- Maps
  - An Ortelius Map – Nos. 70 and 71.
  - Bible Lands and the Cradle of Western Civilization, 1938
  - Far East, 1952
  - Leardo Map of the World – leaflets, 1928
  - Map of Poitiers, n.d.
  - Pacific Ocean, 1952
  - Rocky Mountain National Park – Colorado – Topographic Map, 1922
  - United States Map, 1939-40
- Newspaper and Magazine Clippings
  - 1930s & 1940s - Some with annotations
- Note Cards
  - Relating to Froude Article & Class Notes, n.d.
- Pamphlets and/or Leaflets
  - Guide to Tennessee Historical Markers, 1954
  - L’Abbaye Saint – Wandrille
  - Little, Brown and Company, 1936
  - Marks of Merit, n.d.
  - Samuel Brannan and the Golden Fleece
  - University of Texas Bulletin, 1920
  - Warburg Institute, n.d.
- Political Campaign Literature
  - 1960 United States Presidential Election
- Thesis
  - “A List of Sheriffs for England, 1066-1154” submitted to Yale University, May 1, 1905
- Photographs - 70
  - Abbaye de Villesalem (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chauviguy (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Civaux (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Confluence of Vienne & Loire (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - d’Aquitaine Bordeaux (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Flugel at Nice’ (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fortevrault, Eleanor & Henry (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Leucloitu (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Poitiers (Vienne) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Talmont (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Tivoli (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Verona (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Vezelay (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Postcards (individual) - 156
  - Abbaye de Jumieges (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Angouleme (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Assisi (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Avanton (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Beaumont (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Beruges (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bonnes (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bordeaux (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Chartres (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Chateau-Larcher (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Chinon (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chouppes (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Cloisters (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Dissais (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Fontaine-le-Comte (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - FontevraultIteuil (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Jaunay-Clan (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Jazeneuil (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Limoge (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Limousine en Barbichet (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Limousines en Barbichet (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Lusignan (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Marcay (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Montamise (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Montmorillon (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Niort (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Nouaille (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Poitiers (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Poitiers (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Roma (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Saint-Benoit (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Saint-Maurice-en-Gencay (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Sanxay (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Savigny-Pevescault (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - St. Hilaire – Poitiers (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Switzerland (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Talmont (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Usson-du-Poitou (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Vernon (Vienna) (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Vouille-La Bataille (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Vouneuil-sur-Vienne (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Vouneuil-sous-Biard (Vienne) (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Unidentified (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Postcards (in booklets) - 6
  - Basilique de Saint-Denys (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - La Sainte Chapelle (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Real Armeria I (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Real Armeria II (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Real Armeria III (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Bayeux (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Lantern Slides - 47 (Box 5)
- Johnston Family Papers – Martha Hall Johnston Walker (his mother)
  - December 11, 1860 (Box 6)
  - January 3, 1861 (Box 6)
  - January 22, 1861 (Box 6)
  - January 28, 1861 (Box 6)
  - February 14, 1861 (Box 6)
  - March 6, 1861 (Box 6)
  - March 13, 1861 (Box 6)
  - April 10, 1861 (Box 6)
  - April 29, 1861 (Box 6)
  - May 6, 1861 (Box 6)
  - May 13, 1861 (Box 6)
  - May 22, 1861 (Box 6)
  - June 1, 1861 (Box 6)
  - June 5, 1861 (Box 6)
  - June 7, 1861 (Box 6)
  - August 7, 1861 (Box 6)
  - December 28, 1861 w/attached notations (Box 6)
  - February 5, 1862 (Box 6)
- Johnston Family Papers – Martha Hall Johnston Walker (his mother)
  - Scrapbook – presents to her in 1853 when about to leave Smyrna for America.
  - Turkish Pictures - 16